Guide to the NSF ADVANCE Project for Institutional Transformation of Rice University records, 2004-2010 UA 330
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
NSF ADVANCE Project for Institutional Transformation of Rice University records
2004-2010
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice University
UA 330
2 Linear Feet 3 boxes
The collection consists of materials created by participants in the NSF-funded ADVANCE Project, which was undertaken to increase the participation of women faculty and faculty of color in the departments of science, technology, engineering, and math at Rice University. There are records of meetings, surveys, workshops, research articles, and electronic versions of sponsored events.
Biographical / Historical
The materials that constitute this collection were created when faculty members at Rice University applied to the National Science Foundation for a grant to fund efforts to increase the participation of women faculty and faculty of color in the departments of science, technology, engineering, and math. In mid-September of 2006, a grant of 3.3 million dollars for a five-year program was awarded.
Under the leadership of Principal Investigator Dr. Kathy Matthews, Rice University Dean of Natural Sciences, and Jan Rinehart, Director, committees of current women faculty were formed to gather information and to plan activities. Study participants gathered employment and salary data, surveyed women faculty about the campus climate, and researched literature on pertinent issues. In addition they planned and carried out a Triad Mentorship Program, Department Chair Training, and workshops. The first was titled Negotiating the Ideal Faculty. The second was a one-day workshop for pre-tenure faculty focused on communications and understanding university processes.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of materials related to the participation of women and minority faculty in the departments of science, technology, engineering, and math at Rice University. The grant was awarded in 2006 to last for five years. Included in the collection are papers from the process of applying for the grant, lists of faculty members who carried out the work that was promised, articles collected during their research, results of comparing Rice to the professoriate at large in gender and ethnic diversity, data pertaining to salary differences by gender, and survey information concerning campus climate. Also included are planning and output information from a meeting with the External Advisory Committee at the end of the first year, along with the recommendations that came from this meeting.
There are also CD's and DVD's containing a W.E.P. Workshop; the April 4, 2007 Symposium of the Dean of Engineering; the ADVANCE External Advisory Committee meeting, May 17-18, 2007; and three presentations by Virginia Valian on Sept. 10, 2008: "Gender schemas and the Accumulation of Advantages," "Power and Politics in Your Department," and "Recruitment and Retention."
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from Dr. Kathy Matthews through Dr. Melissa Kean.
Index Terms
Subjects
Faculty; Universities and colleges
Document Types
letters (correspondence); memorandums; notes; compact discs
- Series I: Administrative Records, 166304
  - Executive Director Search-RESTRICTED, 2006; 166101 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Records of Planning and Proposal for Advance Teacher's Course, 2006; 166102 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Year One, 2006-07, 166103 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series II: Training Manuals, 166305
  - Making the Right Moves: A Practical Guide to Scientific Management for Postdocs and New Faculty, 166104 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Entering Mentoring: A Seminar to Train a New Generation of Scientists, 166105 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series III: Organizational and administrative
  - Proposals
    - Proposal drafts, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Final proposal, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Response to proposal, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Final budget, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Faculty recruiting, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Leadership/Chair training (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Institutional transformation programs (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Comparative data (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Dissemination plan (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Budget/financial (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - AAUP faculty gender equity indicators, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Princeton advisory visit, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Publicity (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Evaluation (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Series IV: Surveys
  - Gender equity, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Academic climate, 2007-2008 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Series V: Workshops
  - Women in Science & Engineering, 2001-06-19 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Negotiating the Ideal Faculty Position, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Baker Institute for Public Policy, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Department Climate, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Faculty Success, 2007-04 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Negotiating the Ideal Faculty Position, 2007-10 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Faculty Career Success, 2008-04-19 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Negotiating the Ideal Faculty Position, 2008-10 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Negotiating the Ideal Faculty Position, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Evaluation: Negotiating the Ideal Faculty Position, 2007-2010 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- SeriesVI: Meetings and Committees
  - Meetings
    - Planning, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Principal investigators, 2007-06 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Committees
    - Committee assignments (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Advisory Committee for Study of Women, 2002-2004 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Advisory Committee on Women at Rice, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - External Advisory Committee, 2006-2007 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Faculty Women's Committee, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Internal Committee, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Leadership Committee, 2007-04-2008 (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
    - Recruitment Committee, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Series VII: Research articles
  - Bibliography (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Faculty (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Gender-Diversity-Equity (Box 3, Folder 9-11)
  - Leadership (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Male-Female Comparisons (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Mentoring (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Women (Box 3, Folder 15-17)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Series VIII: Visual/CD
  - WEP workshop (Box 3)
  - External Advisory Committee [meeting], 2007-05 (Box 3)
  - Virginia Valian: "Gender Schemas and the Accumulation of Advantage", 2008-09-10 (Box 3)
  - Virginia Valian: "Power & Politics in Your Department;" "Recruitment & Retention", 2008-09-10 (Box 3)
  - Deans' Summit: ADVANCE Symposium Dean of Engineering, 2007-04-04 (Box 3)